It started like any other night.
Collateral is a drama, crime, thriller film directed by Michael Mann.
Cab driver Max picks up a man who offers him $600 to drive him around.
But the promise of easy money sours when Max realizes his fare is an assassin.
Vincent, played by Tom Cruise.
Max Durocher, played by Jamie Foxx.
Annie Farrell, played by Jada Pinkett Smith.
Det. Ray Fanning, played by Mark Ruffalo.
Richard Weidner, played by Peter Berg.
Felix Reyes-Torrena, played by Javier Bardem.
Collateral is a 2004 American action thriller film directed and produced by Michael
Mann, written by Stuart Beattie, and starring Tom Cruise and Jamie Foxx.
The supporting cast includes Jada Pinkett Smith, Mark Ruffalo,
Peter Berg, Javier Bardem, and Bruce McGill.
The film follows Max Durocher (Foxx), a Los Angeles cab
driver, and his customer, Vincent (Cruise).
When offered a high fare for driving to several locations, Max agrees but soon finds himself taken
hostage by Vincent who turns out to be a sociopathic hitman on a contract killing spree.
Beattie conceived the film's concept while taking
a taxi home from Sydney Airport.
He shared the idea with producer Julie Richardson, who
showed it to director Frank Darabont.
The film was pitched to HBO but was declined.
It was purchased by DreamWorks but would not see development for three years.
Before the trio of Mann, Cruise and Foxx joined the film, Mimi Leder, Janusz Kamiński and Fernando Meirelles were each
considered as director, and Russell Crowe and Adam Sandler were in talks to star as Vincent and Max, respectively.
Filming primarily took place throughout Los Angeles, and was the first feature
film to be shot with a Viper FilmStream High-Definition Camera.
The musical score was composed by James Newton Howard, with
additional songs from Audioslave and Paul Oakenfold.
Collateral was released in the United States on August 6,
2004, and grossed over $220 million worldwide.
The film received critical acclaim in particular for the performances
of Cruise and Foxx, Mann's direction, and the editing.
Collateral was chosen by the National Board of Review
as one of the top ten films of 2004.
At the 77th Academy Awards, Foxx received a nomination for Best Supporting Actor, while
film editors Jim Miller and Paul Rubell were nominated for Best Film Editing.
The film explores themes of taxi, police, hitman,
hostage, self-fulfilling prophecy.
The tone is intense and dark and emotional.